Guide to the Alonzo B. Cornell papers, 1830-1904.
Cornell, Alonzo B. papers, 1830-1904
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alonzo B. Cornell papers, 130-1940.
773
Alonzo B. Cornell, 1832-1904.
6 cubic ft.
Correspondence and manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, journal, accounts, clippings, notes, leaflets, blotters, and scrapbooks relating largely to Cornell's political activities and reflecting his interest in governmental problems and other acitivities.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Governor of New York.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, journal, accounts, clippings, notes, leaflets, blotters, and scrapbooks relating largely to Cornell's political activities and reflecting his interest in governmental problems, his attachment for Roscoe Conkling, and his hatred for Thomas Collier Platt. There is genealogy, correspondence, various obituaries including Ezra and Alonzo Cornell, items about Cornell University, and items pertaining to Cornell's work with the New York, Albany and Buffalo Telegraph Co. including a journal with comments on the telegraph line and an account book recording personal expenses and stock purchased of the Erie & Michigan Telegraph Co. Also includes correspondence relating to the New York State Committee and State Convention of the Republican Party (1871) and letters (1880-1882) written during Cornell's administration as Governor, concerned with appointments, the veto, various reform or political measures, political treachery, elevated companies, railroad commissions, and other matters. Correspondents include Francis C. Barlow, L.E. Chittenden, Roscoe Conkling, Austin Corbin, Howard Crosby, George William Curtis, Theodore L. Cuyler, Noah Davis, William C. DeWitt, Dorman B. Eaton, Francis M. Finch, Charles J. Folger, Jay Gould, Horace Greeley, Benjamin Harrison, Frank Hiscock, H.B. Hyde, J(ohn) N. Knapp, Seth Low, J.N. Matthews, Levi P. Morton, Albert D. North, George W. Parsons, Jackson L. Schultz, Elliott F. Shepard, Charles E
Also, letters collected for an Ezra Cornell Memorial volume. Alonzo Cornell proposed publishing these reminiscences with a Founder's Day speech delivered by Francis M. Finch. Letters and manuscripts include recollections and memorials concerning Ezra Cornell, solicited by his son, via form letters dated November 30 and December 9, 1887. There is no evidence that these were ever published as a memorial volume. The only paper known to have been used is the reminiscence by Andrew Dickson White. It was delivered as a Founder's Day Address in 1890 and published as a pamphlet the same year. Also a manuscript of Alonzo Cornell's A HISTORY OF CORNELL UNIVERSITY 1865-1900.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell, Alonzo B.,1832-1904.; Acton, Thomas Coxton.; Barlow, Francis C.(Francis Channing), 1834-1896.; Chittenden, L. E.(Lucius Eugene), 1824-1900.; Conkling, Roscoe, 1829-1888.; Corbin, Austin, 1827-1896.; Cornell, Ezra, 1807-1874.; Crosby, Howard, 1826-1891.; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.; Cuyler, Theodore L.(Theodore Ledyard), 1822-1909.; Davis, Noah, 1818-1902.; DeWitt, William C.; Eaton, Dorman B.(Dorman Bridgman), 1823-1899.; Finch, Francis M.(Francis Miles), 1827-1907.; Folger, Charles James, 1818-1884.; Gould, Jay, 1836-1892.; Greeley, Horace, 1811-1872.; Hiscock, Frank, 1834-1914.; Hyde, H. B.(Henry Baldwin), 1834-1899.; Knapp, J. N.J(ohn) N.; Low, Seth, 1850-1916.; Matthews, J. N.; Morton, Levi P.(Levi Parsons), 1824-1920.; North, Albert D.; Parsons, George W.; Platt, Thomas Collier, 1833-1910.; Schultz, Jackson L.; Shepard, Elliott F.(Elliott Finch), 1833-1893.; Smith, Charles Emory, 1842-1908.; Stevens, Simon.; Stewart, William Rhinelander, 1852-1929.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Cornell University.; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company.; New York (State).Governor.; New York, Albany and Buffalo Telegraph Company.; Republican Party (N.Y.); Republican Party (N.Y.).State Committee.
Subjects:
Republican Party Campaign 1871.; Telegraph lines.; Telegraph--New York (State).; Railroads--New York (State).
Places:
New York (State)--Politics and government.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Additional information and a copy of the name and subject index to this collection is available by clicking here. Also contains a list and descriptions of the letters for the Ezra Cornell memorial volume. (1 MB Searchable PDF)
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, 1830, 1833, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1850-1851 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1856-1878 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1880-1881 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1882-1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1885-1889 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1890-1896, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous, 1861-1894 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- A.B. Cornell's Journal kept while he was with the Telegraph Office in New York City, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Telegraph Office Personal Cash Receipt Book, 1856-1857 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, promissory notes, calculations re: Steamboat purchase, Jan.-June 1862 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Gold Mining Company Shares, 1865-1866 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Ulysses S. Grant for President, Republican Campaign Items, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous Items, 1857-1890 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Autobiography of Alonzo B. Cornell - Manuscript copy, ca. 1888 or 1889 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "Some Beginnings of Westchester County History" by Alonzo B. Cornell (including some genealogy of the Cornell family beginning with Thomas Cornell), 1890 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Engraving of Alonzo B. Cornell, ca. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Printed pamphlet: "History of the Electro-Magnetic Telegraph," a paper presented by Alonzo B. Cornell at Union College, Jan. 19, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Political broadside: "Puck's Political Bedfellows and Their Nurse", ca. 1890 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Ezra Cornell Memorial Volume
  - Form letter, clipping, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Adams-Bostwick, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Brewer-Esty, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Ferris-Humphry, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Jordan-Prescott, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Ramsey-Shaw, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Torrey-Warner, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters and typescript reminiscence by A.D. White, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters and manuscripts, Wilder-Wright, 1887-1888 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript history of Cornell University by Alonzo B. Cornell, Chapters 1 to 5, 1868-1899 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript history of Cornell University by Alonzo B. Cornell, Chapters 6 to 12, 1868-1899 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Supplement to the Troy Daily Times re: the founding of Cornell University, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook No. 1. Newspaper clippings. Poetry, early Ithaca history, statement of Andrew D. White asserting that Cornell was indeed a Christian oriented university; obituaries of Ezra Cornell and Susan Linn Sage (Mrs. Henry W. Sage); extensive clippings on the Willard Fiske-Jennie McGraw case and other items., 1866-1882 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook No. 2. Newspaper clippings. Sports events and other Cornell University related news, several pages of clippings re: the Fiske court and will battle: particularly concerning the Fiske mansion which Jennie McGraw Fiske had builty in 1879-1881, 1870-1906 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook No. 3. Newspaper clippings. Clippings re: the Johnstown, Pa. flood of 1899, The Biography of Ezra Cornell by Alonzo B. Cornell, including a folder of cash receipts from the book's sale, and various political articles., 1895-1904 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook No. 4. Newspaper clippings. Political items, obituary notices for Alonzo B. Cornell, Henry W. Sage, James Fraser Gluck and others; Cornell University related news and fields of study; history and government of the University, sports, and former Cornell presidents., 1892-1915 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook No. 5. Obituary notices for Alonzo B. Cornell (he died Oct. 15, 1904), and a Cornell University Library book receipt notice, signed by George W. Harris., 1880-1882 (Box 7)
- New York State Legislative Blotters
  - Jan. 1-Mar. 16, 1880, 1 (Box 8)
  - Mar. 17-Apr. 1, 1880, 1 (Box 9)
  - Apr. 1-May 17, 1880, 1 (Box 10)
  - May 18-June 24, 1880, 2 (Box 11)
  - June 26-Dec. 31, 1880, 2 (Box 12)
  - Jan. 1-Mar. 14, 1881, 3 (Box 13)
  - Mar. 14-Mar. 25, 1881, 3 (Box 14)
  - Mar. 28-May 2, 1881, 3 (Box 15)
  - May 2-June 29, 1881, 3 (Box 16)
  - June 30-Dec. 31, 1881, 4 (Box 17)
  - Jan. 2-Mar. 9, 1882, 4 (Box 18)
  - Mar. 10-Apr. 19, 1882, 4 (Box 19)
  - Apr. 19-June 2, 1882, 4 (Box 20)
  - June 2-Dec. 29, 1882, 5 (Box 21)